Finding Aid for the Program for Art on Film Records, 1951-1999, undated IA20008
Institutional Records and Archives
Program for Art on Film records
1951-1999,
undated
(bulk 1984-1997)
Institutional Records and Archives
Pratt Institute
Program for Art on Film (New York, N.Y.)
Gombrich, E. H. (Ernst Hans), 1909-2001
Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.)
Columbia University
J. Paul Getty Trust
Hockney, David
Haas, Philip
IA20008
120.8 Linear Feet
0.04 GB
Records include correspondence, memoranda, printed matter, minutes, financial and legal documents, films, CD-ROMs, slides, and ephemera produced and collected by the Program for Art on Film, 1951-1999 and undated. Included in the collection are records created and collected by the Program for Art on Film. Among the records created by the Program are correspondence, publications and related correspondence and memoranda, and films. Also included in the records are interviews with filmmakers, in both audio cassette and transcript format, information on two symposia organized by the Program, and records of the Advisory and Managing Committees. Materials collected by the Program include subject files, primarily on art historical topics and film-related topics; information on filmmakers, art historians and artists; brochures and catalogs from film production and distribution companies; information (catalogs, press releases, brochures) on art-related film festivals, both domestic and international; and published materials.
(106 boxes)
Separated Materials
The Program for Art on Film amassed a large collection of books, videos, magazines, journals, and other printed materials. This material was separated from the collection and transfered to the Getty Research Library for evaluation. All eligible material was incorporated into the library collection and is available to researchers.
Acquisition Information
These records originated in accession no. 2004.IA.14. The collection was shipped from the New York Public Library (original box numbers 1-73D) and a storage facility in Long Island City, New York (original box numbers 74-126B). The records arrived in almost no apparent order.
Additional materials was transferred by Nadine Covert in relation to the Art on Screen database. The records were accessioned as accession no. 2008.IA.08. A set of the final version of the Art on Film/Film on Art videos was accessioned as 2011.IA.08. Additional materials were accessioned as 2011.IA.52.
Technical Requirements
Films, video and audio tapes require viewing and listening devices.
Restrictions on Access
The records in accessions 2004.IA.14, 2008.IA.08, 2011.IA.08, and 2011.IA.52, subject to review for permanently closed information, are open to qualified researchers. Requests for access will be reviewed on a case-by-case basis.
The following types of records are permanently closed: records containing personal information, records that compromise security or operations, legal communications, legal work product, and records related to donors. The J. Paul Getty Trust reserves the right to restrict access to any records held by the Institutional Archives.
Scope and Content of Collection
Records consist of correspondence, letters, press releases, clippings, articles, memos, notes, reports, photographs, films, magazines, journals, CD-ROMs, audio cassettes, slides, financial documents, legal documents, curriculum vitae, catalogs, brochures, inventories, books, posters, minutes, surveys, and transcripts created and collected by the Program for Art on Film, 1951-1999 and undated. Included in the collection are records created by the Program for Art on Film (publications and films), and a large collection of records collected by the Program.
The records created by the Program describe the development, production, promotion and distribution of Art on Film projects. The Program for Art on Film produced a number of reference works that are included or mentioned in the records, such as the Art on Film Database, begun in 1984; Art on Screen: A Directory of Films and Videos about the Visual Arts (G.K. Hall & Co., 1992); Art Museums and Media (1994); and The Art on Screen Handbook: Practical Guidelines for Using and Producing Films, Videos and Interactive Programs about Art (1994). The Program's Production Laboratory produced 14 films for its Art on Film/Film on Art series, many of which received awards and all of which are described and included in the records. Among the filmmakers, artists and art historians who collaborated on some of these films are Philip Haas, David Hockney and Ernst Gombrich. The records also describe the day-to-day administrative management of the Program through strategic planning reports and advisory and managing committee meeting minutes, information on the Program's joint ventures with the J. Paul Getty Trust, the Metropolitan Museum of Art, Columbia University and Pratt Institute. The Program's work on symposia, conferences, and educational outreach activities is documented in the records describing Art on Screen and Architecture on Screen, Art on Film, and screenings of its films. The activities of the Production Laboratory are also documented in the records, and can be found throughout all the subseries.
The records also include materials collected by the Program, such as informational materials (in the form of press releases, brochures and catalogs) on national and international companies and organizations that produce and distribute films on art; individual films (both feature and documentary) that take as subject artists or art; and conferences that screen films on art. The "people files" document filmmakers, art historians, and other individuals with interest in film and/or the arts; some of the individuals represented in the records served as evaluators for the Program's publications (including its films). The Program collected a variety of material on national and international film festivals that screen films about art; these are represented in the records primarily by brochures and catalogs. The "subject files" represent material used for research. These records primarily describe artists, films, organizations, art historical time periods and movements. Lastly, the Program collected posters for films (both art and non-art related); these are included in the records.
Arrangement
These records are organized in two series:
Series I. Program for Art on Film and Production Laboratory records, 1971-1999
Series II. Records collected by the Program for Art on Film, 1951-1998.
Administrative History
The Program for Art on Film was founded in 1984 as a joint venture between the J. Paul Getty Trust and the Metropolitan Museum of Art as a pilot project that would eventually become independent from its founding institutions. The Program's purpose was to define issues, develop programs, and disseminate information that would support the effective production and use of moving-image media that contribute to a better understanding and appreciation of the visual arts.
From 1984, the Getty Trust, through a joint venture with the Metropolitan Museum, subsidized the development of the Art on Screen Database and the Program's other projects. The Trust's support made it possible for the Program to offer a range of services to the field for free or at minimal cost during this productive development period under the joint venture, which concluded in June of 1994. From July 1994 through June 1996, the Program was based at Columbia University.
The Program was then established as an independent, non-profit 501(c)(3) corporation. In 1996 the Program affiliated with the Pratt Institute and moved its offices to the School of Information and Library Science (SILS) building, on the Institute's main campus in Brooklyn, New York. Some of the resulting programs enabled by this new joint venture were the Art on Screen and Architecture on Screen festivals.
The Program's first Executive Director was Karl Katz (1984-1992). Wendy Stein served as Program Manager and Nadine Covert served as Special Consultant, Critical Inventory during the same period. In 1992, Covert was named Manager of the Program. Joan Shigekawa served as Coordinator, Production Laboratory, from 1986 to 1990. When the Program moved to Columbia University in 1994, Covert was named Director, and served in this position until 1998, when the program was discontinued.
During its lifetime, the Program's activities included a constellation of complementary services: compiling and maintaining the Art on Screen Database (also known as the Critical Inventory); publishing Art on Screen, the newsletter of film and video on the visual arts; developing filmographies, handbooks, and other publications; reviewing and evaluating moving-image productions on art and architecture; presenting workshops and seminars for educators and museum professionals; and distributing a series of short films and videos involving collaborations between art scholars and filmmakers, produced as part of the Program's earlier Production Laboratory experiment.
Among the reference works produced by the Program were: the Art on Film Database, begun in 1984; Films and Videos on Photography, in collaboration with the Direction des Musées de France, Ministry of Culture and Communication, Paris, in both English and French editions; Art on Screen: A Directory of Films and Videos about the Visual Arts (G.K. Hall & Co., 1992); Art on Screen, a newsletter of the visual arts, and Close-Ups, the Art on Film Database Service supplement of reviews and recommended film titles; Architecture on Screen (G.K. Hall & Co., 1994); Art Museums and Media (1994), a report of survey results; and The Art on Screen Handbook: Practical Guidelines for Using and Producing Films, Videos and Interactive Programs about Art (1994).
The Art on Screen Database provided a unique critical inventory of more than 26,000 international film, video, and multimedia productions. The scope of the database included fine arts, architecture, photography, archaeology, decorative arts, design, costume, crafts, folk arts, and related topics such as aesthetics and creativity. The database was ranked among the top three databases by the Consortium of College and University Media Centers. It appeared in electronic form in 1995 as Art on Screen on CD-ROM (G.K. Hall/Macmillan). [Adapted from Nadine Covert, "Milestones: Activities and Accomplishments"]
Awards; Audiocassettes; Art in motion pictures; Art and motion pictures; Inventories; Magazines (periodicals); Memorandums; Minutes; Correspondence; Contracts; Color slides; Clippings (information artifacts); CD-ROMs; Catalogs; Brochures; Books; Transcripts; Videocassettes; Short subjects; Surveys (documents); Documentary films -- Production and direction; Resumes; Motion pictures -- Production and direction; Motion pictures -- Distribution; Motion pictures (visual works); Motion pictures; Reports; Press releases; Posters; Photographs
- Program for Art on Film and Production Laboratory records, 1971-1999; (bulk 1984-1994); Series I.; 67 Linear Feet; (circa 71 boxes)
  Arrangement
  These records are organized into ten subseries: Series I.A. Administrative records, 1984-1994
  Series I.B. Publications and publication information, 1984-1988
  Series I.C. Art on Film/Film on Art records, 1984-1998
  Series I.D. Art on Screen database records, 1994-1998
  Series I.E. Art on Screen and Architecture on Screen symposia, 1992, 1997-1999
  Series I.F. Interviews, 1987-1992
  Series I.G. Conferences, seminars and workshops, 1974, 1979-1997
  Series I.H. Legal documents, 1985-1999
  Series I.I. Production Laboratory miscellaneous information, 1986-1996
  Series I.J. Miscellaneous, 1971-1979, 1984-1994.
  Scope and Contents note
  Records consist of correspondence, letters, public relations material, clippings, reports, photographs, films, financial documents, legal documents, published material, minutes, surveys, transcripts, and audiocassettes created, published and collected by the Program for Art on Film and its Production Laboratory, 1971-1999. The records describe the development, production, promotion and distribution of Program for Art on Film projects (handbooks, newsletters, databases, and films).
  The records describe the day-to-day administrative management of the Program for Art on Film through strategic planning reports, advisory and managing committee meeting minutes, and information on the Program's various joint ventures (with the Metropolitan Museum of Art and the J. Paul Getty Trust, Columbia University, and the Pratt Institute). The records also describe specific Program for Art on Film projects and publications, such as handbooks and newsletters, databases, reports and resource guides, and various other programs and projects. Among the most visible of the Program's projects were the 14 films created by its Production Laboratory for its Art on Film/Film on Art series, many of which received awards. The Program's work on symposia, conferences, and educational outreach activities is documented in the records describing Art on Screen and Architecture on Screen (that also resulted in publications of the same name), Art on Film, and screenings of its films that took place around the world. The activities of the Production Laboratory are also documented in the records, and can be found throughout all of the subseries.
  - Administrative records, 1984-1994; Series I.A.; 8.75 Linear Feet; (9 boxes)
    These records are listed by subject, and in the order found within the original accession.
    Records consist of reports, minutes, financial documents, and planning documents created by the Program for Art on Film, 1984-1994. Included are strategic planning documents, minutes of advisory and managing committee meetings, reports on the status of various Program for Art on Film projects, fiscal reports, information on cataloging and subscription services, and information on members of the Advisory Committee.
    - Key Program for Art on Film documents:
      - Strategic Planning, 1989 (Box 2004.IA.14-97A)
      - Strategic Planning: Basics, 1989 (Box 2004.IA.14-97A)
      - Managing Committee, 1993 (Box 2004.IA.14-97A)
      - Scenarios re PAF, 1991 (Box 2004.IA.14-97A)
      - Mission Statement, 1988 (Box 2004.IA.14-97A)
      - Crit. Inventory Report, 1991 (Box 2004.IA.14-97A)
      - FY91 Program Initiatives and Key PAF documents, 1989-1991 (Box 2004.IA.14-97A)
      - Advisory Committee Minutes, 1984-1990 (Box 2004.IA.14-97A)
      - Managing Committee Minutes, 1984-1993 (Box 2004.IA.14-97A)
      - Managing Committee, 1984-1993 (Box 2004.IA.14-97A)
      - Monthly Reports, 1992-1993 (Box 2004.IA.14-97A)
      - Monthly Reports, 1993-1994 (Box 2004.IA.14-97A)
      - The Knowledge, 1990 (Box 2004.IA.14-97A)
      - The Knowledge (background reading/research), 1989-1990 (Box 2004.IA.14-97A)
      - PAF/MMA, 5 Year Plan, 1988 (Box 2004.IA.14-97A)
      - Production Laboratory, 1989; 1992 (Box 2004.IA.14-97A)
    - Reports:
      - [Critical Inventory Prod Lab: Seminar: Art on Screen, September 13, 1989, transcript Part I; Seminar: Art on Screen, September 13, 1989, transcript Part II; PAF Seminar, September 1989; Critical Inventory, Production Laboratory, Education Outreach Reports; Art on Film Six Month Status Report, January 18, 1993 (2 copies); 1992-1993 Marketing Plan, Six Month Status Report, January 18, 1993 (3 copies)] (Box 2004.IA.14-99A)
      - Managing Committee Monthly Reports, July 1990-June 1992; Managing Committee Meetings, Minutes, etc., 1990-1993; Managing Committee Meetings, Minutes, etc., 1984-1989, 1984-1993 (Box 2004.IA.14-109A)
        General note
        [In binders that need rehousing.]
      - Advisory Committee Meetings, Minutes, 1984-1990 (complete); Managing Committee Monthly Reports, July 1992-July 1994; Monthly Reports, January 1986-June 1990, 1992-1994 (Box 2004.IA.14-109B)
    - Financial documents:
      - Final Fiscal Reports, 1984-1994 (Box 2004.IA.14-119)
      - Budget worksheets for conferences, pubns., etc., 1987; 1991 (Box 2004.IA.14-119)
      - Database Stats (how to generate reports), undated (Box 2004.IA.14-119)
      - Info re Using Printer for Labels and Searches, 1992-1993 (Box 2004.IA.14-119)
      - Credit Card Tx Info, 1996-1997 (Box 2004.IA.14-119)
      - Credit Applications, 1997 (Box 2004.IA.14-119)
      - Dun and Bradstreet, 1997-1998 (Box 2004.IA.14-119)
    - Cataloging and subscription service information:
      - [BHA information folder], undated (Box 2004.IA.14-98B)
      - Subscription Service Inventory, 1990 (Box 2004.IA.14-98B)
      - Authorities Control Symposium, 1986 (Box 2004.IA.14-98B)
      - Ehtnographic Films: MMA Collection, undated (Box 2004.IA.14-98B)
      - Feature Films w. Art Theme, 1987-1988 (Box 2004.IA.14-98B)
      - Indexing, 1988-1989 (Box 2004.IA.14-98B)
      - Indexing, 1986 (Box 2004.IA.14-98B)
      - Indexing, 1987 (Box 2004.IA.14-98B)
      - Indexing: Current, 1988 (Box 2004.IA.14-98B)
      - Indexing, undated (Box 2004.IA.14-98B)
      - Index Terms to Review, 1990 (Box 2004.IA.14-98B)
      - Cataloging Problems, 1987 (Box 2004.IA.14-98B)
      - PN List, 1993 (Box 2004.IA.14-98B)
      - Costume, 1992-1993 (Box 2004.IA.14-98B)
      - Indexing Procedures; Reference Manual. Museum Video: A Source Book for Museums, undated (Box 2004.IA.14-115)
        [Binders that need rehousing.]
    - Miscellaneous administrative files:
      - [Documents: Critical Inventory of Films on Art, summary of discussions with advisors, correspondence, Managing Committee minutes, Advisory Committee minutes; Production Laboratory documents], undated (Box 2004.IA.14-97B)
      - Production Lab: General, 1985-1987 (Box 2004.IA.14-97A)
      - Managing Comm. and Advisory Comm.: Comments on Prod. Lab. Films, 1988 (Box 2004.IA.14-97A)
      - Michael Kustow Letter, 1986 (Box 2004.IA.14-97A)
      - Production Lab: Michael Kustow, 1986 (Box 2004.IA.14-97A)
      - Joan Office Video, 1990 (Box 2004.IA.14-97A)
      - Press re: Joint Venture, 1984 (Box 2004.IA.14-97A)
      - Advisory Committee, 1984-1991 (Box 2004.IA.14-97A)
      - Advisory Committee Biographies, undated (Box 2004.IA.14-97B)
      - Richard Barsam, 1984 (Box 2004.IA.14-97B)
      - Ashton Hawkins, undated (Box 2004.IA.14-97B)
      - Michael Kustow, 1986-1988 (Box 2004.IA.14-97B)
      - Vincent Scully, 1985 (Box 2004.IA.14-97B)
      - Catherine Wyler, 1991; 1994 (Box 2004.IA.14-97B)
      - Press Release on Joint Venture, undated (Box 2004.IA.14-97B)
    - CD information:
      - CD Documentation, 1996; undated (Box 2004.IA.14-17)
      - Le Louvre CD-ROM and press kit, 1995; undated (Box 2004.IA.14-17)
  - Publications and publication information, 1984-1998; Series I.B.; 18.75 Linear Feet; (18 boxes)
    These records are listed in alphabetical order by publication or type of record, and then generally in the order found within the original accession. The "Publications files" are listed in the order found within the original accession.
    Records consist of publications and related documents, reports, correspondence, forms, contracts, and book design work created and published by the Program for Art on Film, 1987-1998. The records describe specific Program for Art on Film projects, including the handbook Art Museums and Media; the Art on Screen Database (known as the Critical Inventory), and its manifestations in both print and electronic form; information on Architecture on Screen, one of the later projects initiated by the program; Art on Film newsletters, databases, reports and resource guides; and information on various Program for Art on Film programs and projects.
    [Many of the Program for Art on Film publications exist in multiple copies and can be weeded.]
    For additional information on Art on Screen and Architecture on Screen conferences, see Series I.D. Art on Screen and Architecture on Screen symposia.
    - Art Museums and Media, 1994 (Box 2004.IA.14-102)
    - Architecture on Screen:
      - [Program for Art on Film publications, miscellaneous flyers], 1998 (Box 2004.IA.14-102)
        [Architecture on Screen '98 (flyer; multiple copies).]
      - Architecture on Screen: A Directory of Films and Videos, 1994 (Box 2004.IA.14-102)
        [4 copies.]
      - Architecture on Screen Promotion, 1993-1994 (Box 2004.IA.14-116)
      - Architecture on Screen Book (G.K. Hall and Co.): correspondence, 1992-1994 (Box 2004.IA.14-116)
      - Architecture on Screen: Editorial Board, 1992 (Box 2004.IA.14-116)
      - Distributor/Producer Letter: Architecture Book, 1992 (Box 2004.IA.14-116)
      - Architecture on Screen Authors (correspondence, etc.), 1992-1993 (Box 2004.IA.14-116)
      - Architecture on Screen Final Copy: Front matter, articles, title list, undated (Box 2004.IA.14-116)
      - Architecture on Screen: Articles Repro. Masters, 1994 (Box 2004.IA.14-116)
      - Arch. Book: Albrecht article, 1994 (Box 2004.IA.14-116)
      - Arch. Book: Bergdoll article, 1994 (Box 2004.IA.14-116)
      - Arch. Book: Grigor article, 1994 (Box 2004.IA.14-116)
      - Possible choices for Arch. on Screen brochure photo(s), undated (Box 2004.IA.14-123)
      - Architecture on Screen: Repros, undated (Box 2004.IA.14-124)
      - Architecture on Screen: Repros, undated (Box 2004.IA.14-124)
      - AoS Handbook, 1994 (Box 2004.IA.14-124)
    - [Program for Art on Film flyers, 3 boxes, 3 types; 150 (3 groups of 50) of the Pantheon], undated (Box 2004.IA.14-114B)
    - Art on Screen ("Critical Inventory"):
      - Art on Screen handbook, 1994 (Box 2004.IA.14-86 and 87)
        [Multiple copies.]
      - Art on Screen handbook, 1994 (Box 2004.IA.14-86 and 87)
      - Art on Screen CD-ROM 1995 Edition (Box 2004.IA.14-86 and 87)
      - Art on Screen, Correspondence re (contracts submitted, etc.), 1988-1990; 1997 (Box 2004.IA.14-116)
      - Art on Screen Book: Repros., 1992 (Box 2004.IA.14-116)
      - Art on Screen book: Delson article, "Programming Films on Art,", 1992 (Box 2004.IA.14-116)
      - Art on Screen book: Montgomery article, "AoS: Films/TV on Art - An Overview,", 1992 (Box 2004.IA.14-116)
      - Art on Screen book: Covert article, "Reflections on Quality: Evaluating Films on Art,", 1992 (Box 2004.IA.14-116)
      - Art on Screen book: Rickey article, "Celluloid Portraits,", 1992 (Box 2004.IA.14-116)
      - Art on Screen book: Wechsler article, "Art History and Films on Art,", 1992 (Box 2004.IA.14-116)
      - Art on Screen: Distr. Letter and Photo Release Form, 1991 (Box 2004.IA.14-116)
      - Art on Screen: Editorial Board responses, 1990 (Box 2004.IA.14-116)
      - Art on Screen: editorial work, 1990-1991 (Box 2004.IA.14-116)
      - G.K. Hall: Art on Screen Correspondence, 1991-1992 (Box 2004.IA.14-116)
      - Art on Screen: promo, 1990-1992 (Box 2004.IA.14-116)
      - [Art on Screen bookmarks], 1998 (Box 2004.IA.14-102)
      - Art on Screen: A Directory of Films and Videos about the Visual Arts, 1994 (Box 2004.IA.14-102)
      - [Art on Screen materials], 1992 (Box 2004.IA.14-116)
        [Book jacket for Art on Screen book; photos of cover for Architecture on Screen book; folder with proposal for Art on Screen book.]
      - Art on Screen CD-ROM, Promo, 1995 (Box 2004.IA.14-124)
      - G.K. Hall: CD ROM, 1993-1994 (Box 2004.IA.14-124)
      - G.K. Hall: CD ROM, 1994-1995 (Box 2004.IA.14-124)
      - G.K. Hall and Co.: General Info., 1991-1995 (Box 2004.IA.14-116)
      - [Press Coverage: Program for Art on Film Critical Inventory (6 volumes); "Fan Mail" for the Critical Inventory 1985-87 (3 copies), 1988-1989 (2 copies), 1990-1991 (2 copies), 1993)], 1985-1991 (Box 2004.IA.14-91)
      - Sources of info/Inventory, 1985-1989; 1995 (Box 2004.IA.14-94)
      - Critical Inventory, Basic Information, 1984 (Box 2004.IA.14-98A)
      - Critical Inventory Data Form, undated (Box 2004.IA.14-98A)
      - Crit Inventory Data Sheet, 1988 (Box 2004.IA.14-98A)